software engineering radio episode 59 static code analysis.
[Music]
okay, welcome listeners to this new episode of software engineering radio.
this episode is about static analysis techniques, concepts and tools I guess.
and to do this we have a guest, and this guest is Jonathan Aldridge.
and before we talk about the topic, I think Jonathan it's a good idea that you introduce yourself. and talk a little bit about your background, what you do in real life.
all right, thank you. I'm a system professor at Carnegie Mellon University.
where I I do research in the area of static analysis, programming language design.
and also teach classes and in the area of static analysis.
and this material is actually from a tutorial here at Uppsala.
but also from some of my some of the. classes that I teach there.
okay, so I think to get started we might want to discuss why you would want to do static analysis.
and what it is actually, so give us an introduction to the topic.
so static analysis is basically what I like to to think of it as a way of exploring the different ways.
that the program might execute in an abstract way typically.
so you can look at testing as a as a point of contrast.
testing will we'll go through and execute the program with a number of concrete inputs.
and your goal is the tester is to exercise the program in many different ways.
to try to see what it does and see if in particular does what you expect it to.
static analysis is taking a different perspective on this.
instead of taking particular concrete executions, it will execute the program in more abstract ways.
and examine it for for generic kinds of flaws.
the advantages with the the abstract program X exploration you can find a lot of problems.
that you wouldn't necessarily find with particular concrete executions.
because you have to find the right one essentially, you don't think about using the correct input values in order to cover this kind of problem.
exactly right, so what kinds of arrows can you actually find using static analysis?
are there particular types of errors that are that can be easily found, others can't?
well there's a there's a fairly broad range of areas static analysis can find right now.
security vulnerabilities are a critical issue for a lot of companies today.
things like buffer overruns, unvalidated input which could be attained a data or attacks.
for sequel injection, command injection, cross-site scripting.
memory or Zaroff are another common programming error that impacts reliability.
and things like Naldi references, accessing uninitialized data, memory leaks issues.
a lot of developers grapple with that are often difficult to find using testing and inspection and other kinds of techniques.
those are typical ones, but there's a lot of other possibilities.
people have been looking at from the research point of view.
anything from how do you use an API or a framework to looking at exceptions and their flow through the program.
to even looking at design kinds of issues such as violations of encapsulation etc.
and so to just get this straight, this kind of static analysis is not about you know coding conventions.
and and capitals were small letters in variables.
it's really about semantic analysis of what the program does, and not about trivialities in it in the best case.
yes I'm here, there are certainly one can use static analysis to enforce sort of formatting and coding conventions.
and and and people have used that in certain environments where they feel strongly about those constraints.
and what I think the real value of static analysis comes in looking at the kinds of issues.
that the humans are actually not very good at assuring.
you can do a code review and you could find a lots of lots of style issues.
but a code review may find it very difficult to find a memory leak.
because to understand the code you're reviewing you need to know the context.
who allocated this memory, who's responsible for freeing it?
if I let a pointer drop on the ground well you know maybe I'm not the one responsible for it anyway. and so maybe that's okay I have to know the context.
and the context is the most difficult thing to get and in the context of say a source code review.
but how do you actually know this context?
I mean typically code is called from many different parts of the.
system under certain partially convoluted conditions.
how do you actually find out the context in static analysis?
doesn't actually work well, I think that's one of the big challenges in the design of static analysis is how you find the. context.
and there there are a couple of, there are many technical approaches they fall into a couple of categories.
one is simply exhaustive exploration.
if you were as a code review or you could find out the context just by reviewing all the code around.
now you don't have time to do that, but a computer may have time to do that.
certainly it has time to to look at all the code because it's compiling all the code anyway.
in cases where the context is more interesting you have you.
may have a lot of challenge figuring it out just by analyzing the entire program at once.
because it requires say essentially inferring the programmers intent.
a good example is a concurrency analysis how to get concurrency right.
typically the way programmers will make it work is they associate each bit of state with a lock.
and they hold that lock before they access the state right.
not the only way of correct concurrency, but a very common one.
so so to assure a program you have to figure out what's the association between locks and state.
that's something that is very difficult to infer automatically.
but in that case actually having a programmer help you out a little bit can make the static analysis much more effective.
having him help out like annotating the code or having some meta information that have passed to the tool?
precisely writing writing little annotations that talk about for example what kinds of locks are associated with what kinds of objects.
can give the tool just enough information, and then check the consistency of locking from that point on.
so that is probably in line with some of the pro that some of some JS are in the. java world.
where people try to define that certain variables must not be now never ever not expected to be now.
and then you can have some kind of analysis tool that verifies that the variable isn't everyone now.
that's right, is the reference so this is an ideal match for the the kinds of annotations have been added to Java and.net recently.
and I know there's a jsr specifically looking at annotations like not null too.
and I think they were thinking of locking issues as well in that context.
yeah that yesterday I was in the in the tutorial by Brian gets about Java concurrency.
and he said he showed this this additional annotation on a member variable that says guarded by such and such.
but the problem is that this is just documentation.
so there is no easy way of finding out whether when you access the variable the lock is actually held.
and and my thinking in that in that context was that maybe one of the.
problems is that today's languages aren't declarative enough.
you have a lot of behavior you know in more or less understandable and obvious lines of code then that lock or don't lock.
so would you agree that that may be making languages more explicit about third.
and saying things such as concurrency that this would make such analysis things simple to implement? I think that's absolutely true.
in fact if you look at concurrency analysis in Java it's considerably easier than concurrency analysis in languages like C++.
because Java has a built-in synchronization construct.
and so what single analysis can build in the concept of synchronization.
and check the common idioms that people use.
now of course one doesn't have to use the synchronization statement bear in Java.
one can use library abstractions for locks like the ones have recently been added to Java.
and of course that only makes concurrency checking more more challenging.
but certainly raising the level of abstraction can help the analysis.
okay but we were talking about idioms and conventions that are documented, that brings up the question.
how many false negatives do you actually get?
I mean people might use a convention 90% of the time, but in the rest the.
code may not necessarily be wrong. they just weren't using the conven.
and this is one of the the.
things that has given static analysis a bad name sometimes.
but saying it sort of reduces the things you can actually do it forces you to code in a special way.
is that still true?
I think that's that's clearly one of the.
big challenges for static analysis.
and I think in a sense it's a fundamental limitation.
because the static analysis all static analysis basically is looking for some kind of pattern of correct usage.
and if you have a what's called a sound analysis one that that will tell you if any error in a particular category.
if there is such an error in your program it has to find particular patterns that are reasonable to check right.
the analysis will terminate and and give you a response and in a short amount of time and so forth.
but unfortunately then of course as you said there are other patterns that could be used that you don't encode.
now I don't think this is necessarily a huge problem in principle.
because I think human engineers work the same way right.
I don't know very many human engineers who reason about a concurrent system by actually considering all the interleavings between threads.
that impossible, and whether any of those could lead to a problem.
that's right, they actually use these higher-level patterns themselves.
and so while it may take us some work to figure out what all those patterns are that engineers are using.
if we can do that then I think we can get an analysis with acceptable e low false positive error rates.
mm-hmm yeah that don't the other thing from a software engineering point of view of course is that there's nothing. if there's parts of the.
program that you can't assure with static analysis don't try to assure them necessarily with a static analysis.
if you need to do things a different way all that means is that you know maybe for your reviewing or your testing methodologies. you spend a little more time in that part of the.
program. and the static analysis reduces the effort you have in the rest of the.
program.
yeah so you you find the stuff that static analysis is good for with static analysis.
and you have more time for the real health problems.
that's right, I think the the the best use of static analysis in an engineering context.
is to arrey what computers do best which is being very thorough and complete.
and they're checking with what humans do best which is the insight behind the correctness of the. program.
that might be expressed in annotations or or you know might be put to work in these you know detailed examples.
or patterns that perhaps the static analysis might not catch.
so how does static analysis actually work?
in the slides that we were using as a basis for this interview.
I see terms like termination, soundness, imprecision.
it seems like these are the the core concepts in implementing such tools.
do you want to elaborate a little bit about this maybe three principles or whatever you call these?
sure well so these are qualities one would like to have in a static analysis.
termination obviously you want it to run and in you won't want it to terminate ideally in a reasonable amount of time.
you want you'd like your analysis to be sound and that it doesn't miss errors.
because the real strength the computers of course is their exhaustive nests.
and so while not all analysis can be useful without being sound is certainly a desirable characteristic when you can get it.
now precision is the last one, and this goes to really the cost-benefit trade off.
your your static analysis is going to tell you a lot of errors you'd like it to be as precise as possible.
in other words one that gives you an area you want it to be a real error.
so the question is how do you how do you get all of these.
and and that that goes into the details of how static analysis works.
essentially the core idea behind static analysis is one of abstraction.
you want to take the program and look at the ways in which it can execute.
but you want to look at those more abstractly.
an example might be let's see say you were doing an array bounds analysis to avoid buffer overruns.
you might try to keep track of variables in the program that might be indexes into the array for example.
and whether each one of those variables is less than equal to or greater than the bound of the. array.
and so your abstraction might be a very simple abstraction.
and and a realistic checker would actually use more interesting ones, but let's pick this one for just as a simple illustration.
so you you you've reduced your variable which might be an integer with two to the thirty two states right.
to just three states less than equal to or greater than.
so basically you're taking you're keeping track of the.
values of all variables that might be used as indexes.
and then you keep track where they are in this range statically.
that's right, and what you do is you essentially execute the program.
and you look given the state of the variables in the previous state and the the. integer expression.
what can you tell about the states in this abstraction in the next state?
okay okay, and you you propagate that around the program.
until you've seen all the different states of the variables and all the states they can reach at every point of the. program.
okay but um isn't that a problematic abstraction given that you might add indexes or add variable values to index?
so if you only know it was less than the maximum possible value and then you add five, you don't know anything about it right.
so this goes exactly to the problem of abstraction right.
because when we abstract we lose some information.
and that's both the strengths of static analysis.
because abstraction is what allows us to be exhaustive essentially.
we've reduced the essentially infinite number of states in a real program to a finite number of states.
which that means we can now explore them all in some sense right.
so we can we can be completed and exhaustive, but we've lost a lot of information about the details.
and so as you say as soon as we add a constant we might lose all information about the range of this thing.
and we might be we might get a false warning.
I guess the key thing here is to find the right abstractions.
and that's probably where the the tools need to be smart.
but lots of experience goes into how the tools actually choose their abstractions.
exactly, so a more a more realistic abstraction although one that's also more computationally intensive expensive.
for this example would be Pressburger arithmetic essentially addition and multiplication by constants.
because that's a a kind of arithmetic that is expressive enough to represent a lot of the.
things you actually see index indexing arrays.
you know maybe not complicated multiple dimensional arrays, but but fairly simple arrays you can express with this.
and the big benefit is that it's decidable, so you can run an analysis that will will terminate and give you response.
and and it's also abstract because it doesn't look at one particular execution.
it looks at the relationships between variables mathematically or algorithmically.
and so it can see if there's a corner case that you might otherwise a missed that's that is an error.
so again to look at this from from another perspective.
isn't is it fair to say that one of the main problems is that programs as we use them today don't necessarily represent the intent of the.
programmer. so you have to kind of reverse engineer what the programmer wants to do.
in order to limit the state space in which the program should or can be?
yes I think I think that's exactly what a lot of analysis is trying to do.
it's trying to you know the engineer wrote the code.
and they were probably thinking about the correctness of issues like lengths of arrays and no pointers and memory dereferences.
and they probably had abstractions, the problem is of course some of those might have been wrong.
and so what analysis is trying to do often is reconstructing those.
sometimes with annotations from the programmer, sometimes more automatically.
and and then verify them, of course you could say well let's just put all the intent in the program.
but of course expressing intent is expensive.
yeah but but um so you have to choose a compromise right.
but so just to compare this to other validation approaches.
if you consider like the the model-based world where people use formalism such as state machines or Petri Nets to express behavior.
and maybe some higher-level constructs to describe dependencies.
you can then run the analyses on model level.
and because they are less cluttered with detail and more related to the actual problem domain.
so they represent the intent better, you can probably more easily do these kinds of analyses.
so the central challenge, although the the reason why code analysis probably more complex.
is that these domain-specific abstractions aren't there anymore.
you have reduced things to a very low-level way of expressing things, so you have to reconstruct all these things.
yes I think that's absolutely true.
and where you have a higher level model there's a lot of benefit from applying analysis at that level of abstraction as well.
I think the challenge is that not all programs not all domains can be captured in these simple sort of state machine like abstractions right. some at some point you need Turing completeness.
hmm, and then at that point you have to bottom out in code and what are you gonna do you need some kind of analysis.
M hmm, so it's huming that we have actually well left this abstract model level of abstraction and gone into the code.
then we have things like conditions and loops and things which sort of make the number of cases the number of paths explode.
how does static analysis deal with these cases?
well this you know with the intention of terminating in an in a finite time absolutely.
and this is one of the major challenges, so the.
key is it goes back to abstraction.
if you think about analyzing a loop one thing you might do is is run through it once.
run through it a second time, run through two third time and and gradually explore all the paths.
but but of course you don't know when to stop cuz they're good enough in a number of times through loop.
the trick is when you're actually analyzing program variables more abstractly.
you only have a finite number of states the program could be in.
and so your index which is incrementing you know plus one every time you go through the loop.
now you know it only goes through two or three states.
and now when you go around again it's in one of the.
states that's been and before.
States at this level of abstraction level introduced giving your understanding of the. program exactly.
and your understanding the problem you're trying to check.
because the abstraction you use for array bounds may be completely different than the one used for concurrency.
but the abstraction is key because once I come around the loop and I've already been at that point in the loop at that state.
then I know that even though the concrete program may go through the loop many more times.
it won't change what I know about the values in the abstract space any more than it already has.
and so I can stop my analysis but still represent all the possible executions.
that may have gone through the loop many many more times.
so the key again is to find the right abstractions.
or even to have a tool that finds the right abstractions from the source code extracts them.
and then partitions the cases in the path according to these abstractions.
exactly, and a lot of a lot of recent state-of-the-art research and static analysis has been looking at novel abstractions.
novel ways of representing abstractions, ways of inferring as you said abstractions automatically from the source code.
das that actually work in practice, I mean in a non-trivial system for a number of cases that actually is useful?
absolutely, so one of the one of the key ideas in a recent recent static analysis is the.
idea of counter example guided abstraction refinement.
it's a it's a mouthful, but the idea is that it's a way of finding precise abstractions automatically from from program text.
it's used in most notably perhaps in the Microsoft slam tool now part of the. static driver verifier.
which you can download from the Microsoft website if you're building device drivers.
it's a it's a tool basically for encoding device driver rules and making sure you write those drivers correctly.
but the internal piece of the.
abstraction works and that tool is is very interesting.
the basic idea is you start with an abstraction that isn't really tracking very much about the program.
maybe you're you're looking at whether you acquire and release a lock.
and you discover there's a path through the program where you lock the lock and then you go and lock it again.
and that second time would be a deadlock and in some implementations of locks right.
so that would be an erroneous path.
but it turns out that if you reported that to the user in some cases it might be a false positive right.
because it might be that those are both in an if statement right.
okay yeah yes, if you take one branch then your to take the other way. so you're never actually going to lock it twice in a row.
so the idea and counterexample grata Depp's traction refinement is from this error path generates a counterexample.
essentially a place where there's a it generates a path through the program that that exhibits this error.
which you can then do is then do a different kind of analysis that symbolically executes the program along that path.
one sees if that path is actually feasible.
uh-huh, and you might discover oh there's this predicate that says you know it's this flag that means I can't go both places at once.
because I check flag is true on one path and flag is false on on the second branch right.
so in that case that tells me this flag is an interesting piece of data that I should be tracking.
and now I'll do the analysis again and I'll track the value of that flag. and I'll discover oh there's actually no error in this node.
so that's a way of discovering abstractions automatically.
do you have some kind of numbers and impressive case study where you can say.
you know there was this project or development team and they had so many bugs.
and then they used static analysis and the world was so much better.
so is there something you can you know tell us off the top of your head.
that convinces listeners that this is really something that is working well?
I think exhibit a for me is the way that Microsoft has used static analysis in their development of the.
windows process monitor.
das originally at Microsoft Research has recently in the last year or.
two led a team developing static analysis for the windows team.
and they've applied a lot of these ideas to some of the most vexing bugs that Microsoft exhibits.
things like buffer overflows in terms of you know security holes other kinds of memory management problems.
and they've they've applied this set of tools comprehensively throughout their process in many ways.
so you have to run the static analysis tools before you check in code.
and the code actually has to pass analysis before you can check it in.
so it's it's a part of the. process.
there there are other analyses tools that run over the main main branch of this source code for Windows.
and generate different kinds of errors.
and the great thing is you know if you're Microsoft and and you're really sick of shipping out a bug fix every month right on on a particular schedule.
yeah right, it's it's it's just not good for your image.
and it costs your customers thousands of dollars and millions of dollars in time to upgrade their software.
and even more when an actual bug escapes and and gets that in the wild right now.
so you're very motivated to fix these.
and static analysis I think is is giving you the potential of reducing those dramatically.
even to zero in the case of a sound analysis for again four classes of errors that can be checked this way.
mm-hmm, so so Microsoft actually uses this approach today in all of their products or?
I don't have information to say all of the. products.
I know the windows team, I know it felt everything filters within that organization.
from the windows team to other parts so I'd expect offices is using these tools and some of the.
other teams as well.
and are these tools available for everybody to use?
some of these tools are, there's a tool called pre fast which is which will run on your desktop.
it's included with the team edition of Microsoft Visual Studio 2005.
pre fast is also available as part of the. Windows SDK which you can download.
even without if you if you don't have the team edition of the.
Microsoft Studio tool. so that's something you can use.
and what's interesting is that the the buffer overrun checker actually uses the same ideas.
that I was talking about in terms of expressing design intent in your source code.
there's a language called standard annotation language or Sal.
this was developed at Microsoft and is used by pre fast.
in which you can associate say the length of an array you have to a function with some other parameter.
that you also pass that function.
and then the analysis uses that little piece of design intent to check the function.
and make sure that any array access is within the function are consistent.
okay, so after talking about these conceptual issues and the theory so to speak let's now move to to practice.
in the sense that you probably have a good overview over the tools that exist for the various different platforms and languages.
so do you want to give our listeners a quick overview of which tools exist?
and maybe what are the characterizing features and we'll put the links to these tools into the show notes of course.
certainly, there's I think one of the.
most exciting things today is that we are seeing more of these tools come out.
and be available to developers.
and they range from open source tools that you can download for free.
to desktop tools like pre fast that you can and the static driver verifier that you can download from places like Microsoft.
to enterprise scale analysis tools that you know are packed with a wide variety of other features.
so I don't claim to to be comprehensive, but I'll tell you some of the tools I think are the. most prominent in this space.
I think at the open source world findbugs may be the most prominent.
is actually published in uppsala a year ago, as the name suggests is looking at bug finding.
their slogan is their slogan is finding bugs is easy, and they have some some data to back that up.
the great thing about fine bugs obviously it's free.
there's a large community that's contributed to it.
and the big thing for an organization is that you can go ahead and adapt this to your process.
your set of tools whatever they may be.
you can customize it with analyses that you write yourself. and that's a real value.
because a lot of the the biggest bang for the.
buck is is taking those ideas that those concepts that are most important.
you know with the set of libraries you use, the set of coding idioms and patterns in your organization.
the set of problems in the domain you're facing and write static analyses simple ones that that capture those those kinds of problems.
mmm-hmm, fine he's also has a very large selection of already-built analyses.
generally fairly simple analyses this is not science well.
they're the kinds of bugs I mentioned earlier.
okay in terms of you know array bounds errors, memory errors, simple kinds of concurrency errors.
what's what's interesting about fine bugs is they they tend to be very local analyses.
local meaning only analyzing within a procedure or or within a small snippet of byte code.
and by the way it's pub Java, I think we did your job.
yes that's a very good, so uh other tools for other languages perhaps?
but so you're not going to find some of the.
really deep bugs that reach across procedures and so forth. although it's it's but it could potentially be extended to some of those.
okay um but I think there's a lot of value to be had potentially there.
okay in the world of commercial tools there's there's a set of a number of tools that are really aimed at the enterprise.
Coverity is one that builds on some research coming out of Stanford University.
some of their strengths are focused on C and C++, low false positive rates.
they're not gonna waste your time with a lot of error messages that are bad that are useless. another one in kind of the.
same space is grammar check code sonar C C++. and Aida Aida okay.
yes that's right,
and it's surprising there's a number of static analysis research based on an ADA.
a spark aid as another tool, Lyford I know knows much about. one of the.
reasons is probably that it's easier to analyze than C++. I'd I'd guess?
well I think in the same vein as Java it's a statically typed language with more reasonable semantics.
yeah and the other easier might be that it's used a lot in these safety critical environments like in the military area.
where validations are probably even required sometimes?
that's right, and in listeners who are building embedded systems may find that the quality constraints of that domain.
are such that static analysis becomes even more worthwhile.
mm-hmm, so so a lot of these tools actually have significant constituencies in that in that area.
clockwork is another tool in the space. clockwork focuses I think equally on security and n bugs.
they have C C++ and Java support.
and they talk a lot about support for enterprise tracking bugs over time.
some architectural visualization which i think is a nice a nice feature.
to prevent bugs from coming in the future as well as ones that are there right now.
looking at tools more focused specifically on security, although they'll find some some coding bugs as well.
fortify and ounce labs are both in this space.
fortify actually has this treated strategic relationship with fine bugs.
so I don't know there may be some coordination coming there at some point.
fortify will handle c-sharp as well as cease C++ and Java.
and some web database web and database languages.
so a lot of cross-platform compatibility there.
for embedded systems we were mentioned mentioning before as a tool called poly space.
which is more specifically focused on embedded systems.
they support data as you see, and they'll be focusing on some issues like integer over-and-under flow.
which might sort of fall below the radar on a lot of systems.
but if you have an embedded system and you don't want your rocket to go off course.
then that's a critical issue for people in this domain.
and for those we don't know this is a real case right?
so that's right, I think you're around five that was the problem there.
that's right, so so poly spaces is may have the answer there.
and of course the when you're in the bedded space some of these vendors will will err more on the side of reporting more possible warnings.
at the expense of having more false positives, which is probably a good idea for safety crew.
exactly, and so I've talked with people in poly space and they say. you know this is this is a trade-off that we've explicitly taken.
which is exactly the right thing for the domain they're targeting.
but it's it's a trade-off you have to make based on your your specific needs.
but when I would took a look at quite a lot of static analysis tools that are targeted at finding bugs.
there are also static analysis tools that are targeted at sort of helping you visualize understand the design the architecture.
it's both called static analysis, are there relationships between the tools between the companies?
I mean the target is obviously different but still?
yes I think it's certainly true that some of the. same techniques apply.
grammar Tech which I already mentioned has some support for say visualizing the in their code.
so in their code surfer project product they have support for looking at the aliases in your program, the runtime heap structure.
there's also products that are looking more at software architecture.
two of those are latex which is a takes the idea of design structure matrices from engineering practice in many different fields.
and we'll will show you the degree to which your system Falls say a layered architecture.
I see yeah, basically they'll they'll layout to your modules at a high level of abstraction along a couple of axes.
and show you at two intersections in those axes where one depends on the other.
and if you can lay out those modules so that all of the interactions are along the lower lower left and the. triangle.
for example if you if you can visualize that you then you you have a layered architecture.
but it can be very interesting to see where say cycles in your architecture are.
because those might be points at which things might be more difficult to evolve or there might be more dependencies.
so this sounds to me a little bit like this heuristic stuff like cyclomatic dependency and all these kinds of things.
again that that's out of the.
scope of what we've been discussing today.
but that's another way of analyzing software but not for PACs but rather for maintainability complexity and stuff.
that's right, in heuristics one else has be careful with heuristics.
because one can one can optimize the heuristic without optimizing the code itself.
but they can also tell you point you to places where you might want to look more close.
yeah but I think the similarity here we actually finding bugs by making assumptions about patterns of usage.
because that's also heuristic in a certain way?
yes that's true, I think one could point to a difference.
in that one can validate that certain patterns lead to actually prove that there are no there are no bugs in a system all right.
yeah whereas metrics such as cyclomatic complexity are not directly related to if it's redness in the same way.
or around quality?
right but there's a there certainly is a relationship.
in that understanding the way to engineers typically build software in the way good software is is typically built.
as is the thing is requires understanding of the.
patterns of usage at a deep level.
okay, so now that we took a look at the tools how do we actually go about introducing static analysis into your company into your development teams?
well I think that's a very there's a very tricky question because there's a cost to using static analysis tools right.
the cost of running them, the cost of paying for them.
but most importantly the cost dimension your time looking at the output seeing if these errors are real.
and it's so sorting through the false positives.
and so it's important to be very careful about how to introduce this.
I think a big part of it is choosing the right tool.
choosing a tool that's well designed that fits the needs of your organization.
and actually doing a little bit of customization to making it fit in.
if you take fine bugs off the shelf for example you'll see there are literally hundreds of checkers in there.
many of those may produce false positives for you either because you don't care about them.
they're not a problem in your domain, you commonly use idioms that don't match when the analysis is looking for. can you give an example?
I thought it bug is a bug no matter what the context?
well uh errors in using concurrency or not bugs if you don't have multiple threads in your program as a perhaps trivial example.
but okay so these checks sort of assume that there are several threads without checking that the threads are there.
and then saying if there is a thread second thread calling the same method then there would be a problem.
that's oh that's right, well especially for a very simple kind of analysis that just looks very locally.
um it may not be aware of whether you're actually in the context of a multi-threaded system.
okay there's certainly many more examples.
but some of the.
things that find bugs my check for might just be you know generally considered bad practice.
but perhaps in your specific setting it's not an issue.
or you may disagree with the authors of the.
analysis about what's good.
okay so so again this is about heuristics which are also always sort of subject to opinion in in some cases.
yes so but what you'll find is the typical pattern of an organization.
is they'll take a off the shelf tool like this.
and they'll have to say these are the analyses that are really the points of pain for us.
those the ones we're gonna turn on.
those might even be the ones that we integrate into a process in some way.
and like saying all of these must be dealt with before we transition from no coding to testing.
or testing to release in the software life cycle of standardizing the usage of the. tool.
and integrating it into the enterprise-wide process is exactly another piece.
is is really winning the hearts and minds of the. developers if you?
yes, so starting with a core team of developers who are willing to experiment to try out something new.
given a little bit of leverage leeway for management and get the tool working well with those developers. and then use those as evangelists in the rest of the.
organization.
for a larger organization you're not going to be able push something like this strictly from the top down.
yeah I see it has to work well, but you also have to get some people behind that.
they're willing to say hey look you know I've been coding here for ten years.
and last week the static analysis a bug a buffer overflow right in critical code I introduced five years ago.
and you know let me tell you I didn't want to wait until the hackers found that one. yeah it's a time bomb.
so I think stories like that when you find analysis and it's you know it's really focused on the issues that are critical for your company.
for your setting that's when you're gonna be able sell it.
and that's where you can really justify the cost in the investment in this technology.
so sort of get buy-in of some developers and have them tell the others how created book?
yeah that's right, I think what excites me about static analysis is that the technology is just getting to the point.
where we can address some really deep problems.
mm-hmm, I give the example in my tutorial of fluid the fluid research project from Carnegie Mellon which is focused on concurrency.
yeah a concurrency is notoriously difficult to deal with.
is certainly calm and it's because everything is non-local.
you know you have interference between threads running in different parts of the.
program.
you have you know this complicated design intent relationship between the locks and objects that you have to track.
and if you have a bug you know you may find it you may run a thousand tests and not find it.
but you can call your software and it gets at a million times a day.
and now it happens every couple of hours or it happens in the release version but not in the debug version. and all signs of with?
yeah that's right, that's why we have this term of the. highs and back.
you have my robot yes trying to measure the box changes to the back itself? exactly.
so this kind of error is exactly the one that static analysis is is as good at applying. and the fluid technology is is being actually commercialized right now.
hopefully you'll be able buy it from a company called sure logic and E and in the near future.
but I think we're seeing from that and from some of these commercial companies from the experience at Microsoft.
static analysis is really maturing it's becoming practical.
it's hitting the problems that are really hurting development organizations.
and I think within the next 5-10 years we're gonna see it become a ubiquitous part of the. quality assurance landscape.
that sounds really cool because it sounds like it's true very helpful very useful.
and once the false-positives and false-negatives already used.
sounds like it's there's no downside to using actually.
that's right, and it's you know it's not a silver bullet.
Quality Assurance is always gonna be hard.
um there's some I we should there's something we should talk briefly about as actually the applicability of static analysis.
there are problems too which is very poorly suited.
problems where the property you're trying to assure doesn't fit into a well-defined pattern that works across many programs.
and as you know sort of worth compiling into an analysis.
classic you know UI testing functional does it give me the answer I wanted that kind of testing?
yes I realize that conformance to the rhymings does it look like users wanted to look is it well usable?
into to this other thing obviously exactly.
but we already have testing and review methodologies they're very good for assuring those kinds of issues.
what we don't have is ways of addressing these kinds of you know memory errors concurrency errors.
so these things we're seeing there's no static analysis really low-level technical domains.
the computers have the strength obviously rather than humans they sort of we tend to lose our way there. it's true exactly.
and so I think from that perspective static analysis is really feel filling a hole.
and and has a potential in those areas to increase quality very substantially.
and and I think this people are always asking for the killer application of a new technology.
and I think for static analysis this killer application is probably going to be.
if you can detect meaningful complex concurrency problems.
because they are as we all know really really tough.
so if the tools get to a point where they can help there.
I think that will be the argument of introducing these types of tools into the process.
especially since everybody has to do with concurrency now because although because of all those multi-core CPUs right.
I think I think it's a issue as you say that's only going to increase.
ok thank you very much for talking to us about static analysis and thanks everybody for listening. thank you.
[Music]
thanks for listening to software engineering radio.
if you want to get more information about software engineering radio or if you want to give us feedback.
please go to our website at se - radio dot net.
you can also contact the team at team at SAE - radio net.
although we prefer entries in our comment system on the website so other people can see what you think.
software engineering radio wants to thank Henning poly for the intro and outro music.
as well as Lipson for providing the bandwidth.
this episode of se radio as well as all other episodes is licensed under Creative Commons license.
see the software engineering radio website for details.